I guess the question is what needs to be
restrained I was like do you say no to
everything to whatever your eye wants to
see whatever your nose wants to smell
how would you know what to say no to
Anthony is why I want to do that chance
yeah depends on what my motivation is so
what would then be the motivation that
you should restrain things other if I
want pleasure
pleasure
well you always want pleasure that's
your starting point about that one thing
you always don't want pain that's the
implicit starting point as well
I want to be so whatever you do it's
done for the sake of pleasure but see
you then
try to say no to every desire and do
everything will also be done for the
sake of pleasure so you'll be denying
everything for the same reason so you want to take
for the same reason so you want to take
you out of it that's that's the the
super the similar of them that be debate
first people first group of their would
they were just eating carelessly and
they got hooked on to debate then the
second group was saw that but then
dismissed with all all the food and
running to the mountains then they
stopped there had to come back it
carelessly and then the the heard that
the Buddha praised is the one that sort
of realizes that and stays within debate
it doesn't need that which is debate so
he needs carefully around the bait so
the reason I bring this up is because
like you know the talk we had about the
violence sensuality and again if people
are not well I guess experienced or
sufficient experience they might fall
into that oh I myself now deny
everything I want to say this no I'm
gonna hear this no I'm gonna taste this
no well why are you saying no to
everything their context from that no
you don't so this the sole purpose of
restraint is to develop context in
regard to your own motivation in regard
to your own desires you have to
understand that you say you want in the
practice restraint is rooted in the same
desires that's what good a man desires to be
that's what good a man desires to be
abandoned by the means of desire craving
to be abandoned by the means of craving
but not simply these are can be
abandoned through the desire or craving
can be abandoned through craving just by
craving you'll abandon craving no you
crave for craving before freedom from
craving initially but if you start
looking in the context of your
motivation the where things are rooted
in what type of intention is behind what
you want to do what you've done or what
you're planning to do that's then how
you basically make craving redundant
and then you fight by avoiding doing
things that perpetuate craving because
not all things perpetuate craving not
all things perpetual ignorance things
that are rooted in lust aversion and
distraction perpetuate craving ignorance
and everything unwholesome but see lust
diversion and distraction are not in
things that you're doing there in your
motivation that makes you do the thing
for those reasons so if you want to find
last aversion delusion it's not simply
by doing this and abstaining from that
it's basically by understanding whether
you are doing it for the sake of loss
diversion or distraction so none of
those none of the last version can be in
things not even in central objects and
that's what would have said put the
target the last desire lust have been
removed from his mind so the beautiful
of District just remains standing there
in the world beautiful no but for that
you need to first restrain your habitual
action towards beautiful a
election away from the ugly a
election distract yourself from you
chill boredom or whatever else but not
for its own sake it's only for the sake
to see how last diversion delusion are
actually on the level of your intentions
your choices not in those things and
that's also like we recover that in our
thoughts but that's also how virtue and
duty is a fetter it's because it's on
the level of you assuming last the
version illusion to be these things that
you're now abstaining from and by
abstaining from it you think that's it
that's all you need to do because you
literally if you think that your mission
is accomplished by abstaining from bad
things you will not look for with the
badness of bad things is really rooted
which is in your motivation for keeping
the precepts or for breaking them
so when we talk about the sensitive
strain yeah you take on The Presets Five
Precepts but ideally you want to take
eight precepts and then within that you
see what mine presents you with things
to do you have to do this a if you say I
will not do anything throughout the day
because everything is routine desire
that will be rooted in desire that's
your desire if you say I should stop
thinking I will not think about anything
that is your thought so you can't just
decide and step outside of the problem
you are the problem your existence is
the problem so you take on the presets
you take on sense restraint and on on
the level of faith furthest and now you
go throughout your day having to do
things and you can't stop doing and you
shouldn't stop doing you just want to
know where the motivation for you doing
those things is rooted and if you want
the okay so how far I go with this well
you go within the presets so if if
things that are presented to you to be
done throughout the day would be
breaking the precepts you just say no to
that you don't need to think too much
about that side of things
no this is against the places that I
have taken on but if it's within the
precepts doesn't mean oh I can do it
justifiably cause it's not breaking the
presets nor is it I must deny everything
because everything is routine design no
you look at the time the same thing
today can be rooted in one thing one
motivation tomorrow it can be routine
another motivation but if only you see
is the thing that you say either always
yes - or no - you're never gonna see you
motivation and that's where the whole
problem is always has been the last the
version delusion can never step outside
of the domain of your attention and
enter these things in the world no not
at all not the slightest always remains
within your intentions if you can
recognize lust for example you can use
regular first you need to recognize your
intention your motivation then you see
if it's lustful if it's an aversive or
if it's sort of deep wanting to distract
itself and then in the background so to
speak you're always watching out for
that exactly what the more the more may
the more effort you make towards
discerning it well
the clearly the discernment will become
which means then you don't need to do or
must stop and figure this out it's all
just basic
the flags will be there already could
you develop them even if you're not not
directly thinking about your motivation
you already know oh this is a lustful
mind and that's the satipatthana he
knows last two - last - mind not lustful
thing in front of him Allah know this
mind that the intent that's what
basically cheetah jet on our
relationship intention and intent in a
general sense it's what mind is already
the direction of some kind always there
is some intention oh there is always a
mind there which means there is always
an intent there so be it means it's
always the intent always has to be
either lust - not lust a version of non
aversion distraction on distraction but
if all you sees things you do things you
don't do and then just meditation
technique on top of it or whatever else
you're never looking at where the
problem actually is and you're never
gonna see it because you assume it to be
in things you're saying no - and that's
why what Oh
so the problem is in the desire desire
towards this - towards of that so I'll
say no to that but now I have a desire
to say no to everything so say no to
that well now I've so say no to that so
you just stop saying no to more and more
things and wand yourself up completely
and equally have no perspective in as
much as if you were engaging with
sensuality mmm that's like the ignoble
way of that self modification and denial
of everything now you have the presets
within that your question thing look I
want to go for a walk as we we say often
as it can be a neutral example why oh
because I'm Restless a bit here now okay
yeah that's not the perfect motivation
but is it sensual motivation is it
because I'm hoping to see sight sound
smell taste touch ins they will excite
me no not specifically just because it's
too hot under this roof and I want some
breeze okay that's not that's alright
I'm not sure how ideal it is or not but
I know that it's not as bad as as like
sensuality is breaking the precepts
so you do it you go for a walk because
you want some breeze you want some
comfort but then next time I want to go for a
but then next time I want to go for a
walk
still same comfort okay but now again
you really you don't now just do it cuz
you've done it before also it is still
rooted in comfort yes still not root any
sensuality of the you know exciting kind
yes but can it perhaps in due to discomfort
but can it perhaps in due to discomfort
and not go for a walk just if you have
strength to ask yourself to provide that
direction or maybe saying no to that but
you do not always say no to it or always
say yes to it because once you decided
to to do so so you always want to see
where your motivation is rooted like why
do I want the breeze in the comforter
because actually I'm sleeping and I'll
fall asleep but if I go for a walk I'll
be awake and then I can spend more time
practicing mindfulness and water
meditation or reading the sutras oh well
that's a good reason now say like with
the Buddha Oh
what if jhana that attained in the past
is the way I think it is the way but I
can now develop it because I'm too
hungry I'm starving I'm in too much pain
so let me get this this rice whatever
the lady off him get some strength so
that I can do it ah that's it that's a
valuable motivation that's a that's a
reason if that's a good motivation oh no
I just want to go for a walk because I'm
bored that's why are you bored why do
you have motivation to get rid of the
border so that's what I mean like I
don't want when we talk about the
senseless train people to jump into
conclusion that you must say no to
everything because that's equally noble
but it doesn't mean or but not saying no
to everything means I can break the
precept sometimes no that's even worse
sensuality is worse than asceticism
but asceticism will not take you out of
the will not approach your craving and
desire in itself either that's only the
first response is giving carelessly
second response is say no to everything
then you go back to stuff you should
have given up and then only that the
response in regard to that in that
simile of the hurt such as the deer herd
it's like oh wait see if I stay within
this but I don't cross certain
boundaries and within that boundary I
discerned motivation and then yet you
will know exactly when things are also
meant and wholesome even before they come
and wholesome even before they come
anywhere near the border of breaking the
precepts see or is maintaining and perspective
see or is maintaining and perspective
which is perspectively maintaining
perspective on your own intent yeah
which is already with you every
situation is already a type of intent
I intend to sit here and continue
talking to you is that in okay so let me
ask yourself now where is that intent of
mine to continue root it what is the
endgame of this so to speak
oh it's recording the damnit over okay
that's fine but that's thing that you
need to know how to have that
perspective to be able to see your mind
your intention and you will know it
while you're doing things well they get
to know that perspective by first
practicing keeping the precepts and
practicing sense restraint then try
creating the boundary within which you
can then discern you can allow your mind
to move left to right within the
boundary not over the boundary and then
you can see our knee moves to left it's
rooted in this when it moves to right
it's rooted in that
suzay keeping physically precepts that
will help you discern your mental well
no knowing what you need to discern will
help you discern on the basis of presets
automatically keeping the presets will
not make you discern it will just make
it keep the precepts for whatever you
feel - well it's a necessary basis it's
not optional you cannot understand
without having kept the precepts
beforehand as the world would say but in
itself understanding will not arise from
it so knowing that you're not supposed
to stop thinking in and watch the
nostrils and just be mindless and adhere
to this knowing that you are supposed to
think about what is the intent behind me
doing what I'm doing right now no you're
not supposed to stop doing everything
say no to everything get rid of
everything but instead understand with
things that are route the things that
the things that are being done or things
you intend to do where are those things
rooted in what is the background of this
of this intention I want to do so so
there's a lustful intention
you know you see that there's a lust for
attention well it's not going to be like
oh there's a last full intention fruit
in my mind it's gonna start with
something specific I heard people
talking there I want to go and see why
what is the intent behind your action to
go and see who is talking there can be
million things it can be or there are
the thieves or hunters came to hunt
animals here so I want to chase them off
well it can be oh maybe just some people
that will be entertaining to talk to ah
so if it's that what is that intention
rooted well it's rooted in me wanting
basically excitement wanted to be
distracted from this neutral feeling
pretty much I'm neither in pain nor in
pleasure but the offer of excitement of
meeting other people or something oh
that's that's exhilarating to me so
that's clearly unwholesome so then you
say no to that you enjoyed that but if
it's on another okay so I will never go
talk to people now no it depends on the
motivation it's rooted so whatever
you're about to do you must question
whatever you're about to do whatever you
are in the middle of doing if you lose
context of why it's done you remind
yourself because you it's not a mystery
the only reason you're still doing these
things are intending to do those things
is because your intent is there is a
necessary basis simultaneously enduring
with it there's one it's become familiar
without having familiar with your
intention about having going through the
whole thinking process over and over
again so why am i moving my exact exact
well is it you want to see the intent
not go to the motions of basically
thoughts that you've done in the past
where you kind of go the sense of the
intent but it's say that now I want to
get up so oh I want so I don't
I must not get up know you might get up
you might not get it doesn't matter
you if you want to get up you get up if
you don't want to get up you don't get
up but you want to know like yeah but
what's my intent why do you want to get
up there does not see when you say the
question why do i why why do i want to
get up people can sometimes immediately
jump into conclusion ah getting up is
bad I must now get up no you just want
to know you will get up you just want to
know why you want
get up so even if it's I want to get up
because of the desire for more comfort
fine there is nothing sensual there is
no your will there is no sexuality we're
just getting up it's still a desire in
as much is when you want to deny
everything so everything is a desire so
if you want to get up you get up but our
going to think about it before you don't
even need to think about it yet for
necessarily you might do it in the
beginning you might have to think about
it in the beginning but once you get to
know that okay it's not against the
precepts to get up okay so why do I get
out for comfort I'm getting up for
comfort okay so the next time but is it
comfort so next up because of comfort
and then you're gonna have a question
inevitably asked like naturally oh so do
I need to go through my day just doing
things out of comfort so next time the
context has now been upgraded so you
want to get up out of comfort can I do
discomfort now you will know why would I
do this conference not like I will not
get up I will endure the pain yeah but
now you have to ask a question you got
to that because that's now the thing
you're doing why do I want to enjoy
discomfort that's a good event like when
when monks would some monks were asking
him to make these uncomfortable
practices mandatory because they're good
and he said no let those who want to do
those things do them and those who don't
want to not do them because it depends
where it's true to them for somebody you
enduring discomfort can be utterly
completely unwholesome and always
routine and wholesome but they will only
know that if they get to discern their
intent so now you don't want to get up
because you want to challenge yourself
with a bit of discomfort fine why do you
see the relationship between the
challenge of discomfort and gaining
perspective what are you just doing it
out of a reaction to your comfort either
way you can do either way because it's
not against the precepts getting up from
comfort of discomfort but you want to
know what is your intent behind so
what is the process of learning how to
design your attention
with that well that I described enough
like it so before I act I must question
my intentions before I yeah but yeah so
if I before I do anything I have to
think wanna do is why I'm doing this
because there's that and then decide
well you might have a think that
initially if you're unaware of your
intent yeah but if you start doing it
rightly you won't even need to verbally
ask your questions you will already see
the intent
that's impressive making possibility of
this action here so you you've discerned
lusts for intention so when it comes
again we're gonna have when you doing
this an action that can be placed on
lust intention you love last day
immediately seen oh this is lust you
don't have to go to that whole process
no no is it lust but is it sure why am I
saying is lust well see that's the thing
where people people will inevitably fall
into that mechanical repetition of doing
the same questions but then they failed
to see that that's now there is an
intent in regard to that and they are
not seeing it so first time you ask
yourself why do I want to get up why do
I want it because of this because and
then you arrive at the conclusions
because of the lost then next time you
immediately but now you don't actually
direct your mind towards intent and then
use the questions to reveal the intent
you now direct your minds towards the
question and you've done before hoping
you will arrive at the same knowledge of
the same intent and now you're doing in
mechanically but now all you need to do
is it the anger any given time just oh
but what is my intent behind this
questioning so why am i questioning now
my motivation in regard to wanting to
get up
do I really don't know whether it's done
for comfort or discomfort or am i doing
it out of this compulsion to go through
these motions that revealed it the first
time and now I feel obliged dutiful to
repeat oh so I already know my intent so
I don't need cause these questions at
all now next time I'm not sure and then
questions was naturally arise but
sometimes intent is much clearer but if
you just adhere now that you always must
do these questioning
you're actually obscuring your in
standby the question you're either way
you will get confused the point is you
don't step over the boundary of breaking
the presets so in the confusion
dispelled you're still held within the
same container you when you restart you
restart already with more experience and
more recognition and more discernment
but if your confusion takes you outside
of the precepts now you need to rebuild
it so that's a they are not optional and
yeah you can do the same practice within
the Five Precepts but it's going to be
much more watered down like if you want
to practice the Dharma on the level that
it matches that can basically make you
gain the right view you need to eight to
the yet reasons but within there again
it's not like no to everything
not at all and that's exactly what would
what if I were to say no to all the
thoughts that are rooted in unwholesome
and what would what would what what if I
were to say yes to all the thoughts that
are rooted in wholesome absence of greed
aversion delusion ah and then the the
tireless energy arose in him day and
night because he was just avoiding
unwholesome thinking also now obviously
there was the Buddha so you could do
that on the level of thoughts means he
didn't even have to worry about a speech
in action because it's already within
that but today's mind when you start you
to start first from your actions then
come to your speech and then eventually
if you calculate that long enough
accurately enough you will be able to
say I have these thoughts appeared in my
mind nothing to do it I didn't intend
them but sensual thoughts
nonsense your thoughts you will know
right away sensual thoughts I don't
delight I don't welcome I don't value
non central thoughts fine take a step
because the mind has to think if you say
I don't think this what are you thinking
that if you think that by avoiding to
think you're somehow stepping outside of
the domain of thought well your basic
yourself deluding yourself
so we did the precepts it's not about
saying no to everything saying yes to
everything was saying no to things you
said no to saying yes to the things you
said yes to automatically it's about
discerning the intent behind your
current situation oh now I need to go
and do some research
what's my intent behind it oh it's some
practical purpose it needs to be
finished okay that's fine you don't even
need yeah but what if what if what if
now if you get into that compulsive what
if this this whole service is
unwholesome what's the intent behind
that compulsion oh the intent is to get
rid of the pain of compulsion so the
intent is a version so the intent is
unwholesome so I'm wholesomely
questioning my intent for the
unwholesome person purpose of getting
rid of the aversion which is not folsom
and you will fall into that confusion or
you will not learn how to step out of
that confusion if you just keep giving
into it and if you if you basically go
start doing the questioning of your
intent mechanically because you depend
or it's easier to just mindlessly
do this this this this the result will
come now what is the intent behind me
wanting that result and that's what once
you actually start doing it rightly this
whole space opens up millions of things
you can do for right reasons and becomes
much less constricted and in the
beginning when it's just I'm not saying
no to everything everything is a desire
everything is a desire but yeah you kind
of have to start like that to some
extent it simplifies the work it does
that's in the beginning and also as I
said like that the the similar of the
deer herd once you realize it's only
things that are routing leaders it's
only this is the bait everything else I
don't have to worry well this is not a
sensual pleasure I don't need to fear it
as the Buddha would say but only once
you accept it okay I need to know the
intent behind acting out of my feeling
acting towards pleasure acting out of
pain because that's where lost aversion
delusion is rooted it's not in the
feeling it's not in the object of your
senses it's rooted in you
being unaware of your intent ignorance
of the intent is what the problem or it
is so once you become discerning of the
intent you simply avoid the one that's
rooted in last aversion delusion and
that's how last aversion delusion will
wither away because they need
maintenance maintenance through
ignorance of what those things are that
you don't even know that you're
maintaining it but now that you know
that this is what things rooted in lust
intent of last hour this is what intent
of lust is you don't do that intent of
lust you don't act out of it when you
tend to last changes it's an intent of
not loss you can do that it might be the
same thing external going for a walk
meeting people to talk to you and then
the last an aversion delusion
distraction will have to diminish you
yeah we're off exactly
say this is just for the purpose of for
people who take on precepts sense
restraint don't do sense restraint
mechanically either because as I said
the same if it's within the precepts the
same thing sometimes you need to
restrain it sometimes you don't it
depending on the intent not depending on
the thing that you're restraining to I
will never look at anything agreeable
yeah why is that why do you have that
intent now so do you blame the agreeable
for your suffering oh yes I do
well that's a mistake isn't it because
suffering is not in the agreeable no
disagreeable suffering is in you either
resisting it or lastly going towards it
so suffering is in your intent so
knowing the intent on account of
agreeable or disagreeable within the
precepts yeah that's how your mind will
have to develop right now and if you get
confused about what my intent was just
step back and see what's your intent in
regard to that and that would be your
intent the current situation intent so
that's where there is no method or
motions or sets of questions you always
ask no sometimes you need to drill
further longer because the intent is
more obscure but more often than not the
intent is right there because the intent
is the basis for the context for
anything you're about to do you're doing
see like my intent to go and talk to
those people over there
I don't need to now think about getting
off the chair opening the gate walking
left right left right
all of that is unified and I'm doing it
mindlessly because it's kept together by
the intent to meet those people down
there if suddenly my intent I don't want
to meet those people I'm gonna go on top
of the hill I will stop going in that
direction and stop doing actions they
will lead me to that intent so the
intent is always there so if you catch
yourself in doubt you realize or action
that's where doubt is a hindrance
because now it covers up what you
already know you already know the intent
are now the doubt
is this compulsion that pressed you to
go through these motions and try to
seemingly clarify intent while the real
purpose is just get rid of the pain of
the doubt all you need to do in order to
get rid of the pain of the doubt is stop
trying to get rid of the pain of the
doubt stop acting out of a version that's it
stop acting out of a version that's it
depart the doubt will have to subside
and you know that you know the
difference like I'm like I'm a
questioning my intent like this I'm
arriving a conclusion but then it sort
of you overdo that and now it becomes
emotion of like I have this compulsion
to keep questioning to keep repeating
the question keep finding the same
answer oh now you're just acting out the
oh now you're just acting out the
compulsion you're not looking for the
intent you're just trying to get rid of
the discomfort which means you're
completely unaware of that intent
so that's how I don't need to fear this
type of pleasure or I don't need to keep
you know having you will towards this
type of discomfort you can actually
become relaxed within the precept within
sense restraint because now you know the
motivation always the intent is there
visible clearly it's like knowing the
mind knowing knowing lustful mind is
lost for mind non last rule is not lost
from that relates it is elated depressed
is depressed
no it's death that's a contain there is
a context it's not a pleasant or
unpleasant and above hindrances I'm not
acting out it exactly not just not just
that is lustful as long as I know my
lust for the intentions I can stall no
no that's the thing if you know the last
as long you don't act that's the effort
you pretend you don't act out enough to
develop that perspective recognize this
is the perspective is the easier will be
to not act out of it people act out of
habitually addictively because there is
no perspective on the situation once the
perspectives increased through your own
effort of reflection Oh
now since restraint is self-evident I
will not so that so you restrained only
the things that are rooted in lost
aversion delusion of the level of intent
you don't restrain every sight every
sound every smell because that's like
starvation that is literally you run to
the home and there is no food and you
die
so in order to know then what you need
to restrain only you don't need to know
the intent because that's what these
things are rooted they need to be
restrained but again you show you my
need to be restraining more than usual
to be on a safe aside that's where the
good would always lean on to the side of
asceticism even if in itself does not
necessarily result in wisdom hope
between the two monks one will eat one
one eat one will eat so he can practice
one say he wanted so he can practice I
praise the one who wanted in order to
practice just in case lean a bit under
but not to become neurotic and say no to
everything because that means how you
lose context than that you don't you
know aware of your own intensity